Chicago Ethnic Arts Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 6: Sound Recordings, 1977
  - Subseries 4: Irish
    - Interview with Frank Thornton about Irish Musicians' Association and Irish music in Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 06, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20584A - AFS 20584B; RYA 0643; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of 2-part interview with Frank Thornton about Irish Musicians' Association and Irish music in Chicago, founded 1957, about his youth in County Kerry, immigration, naturalization in US, music education need for financial support; topic sequence includes where he came from, family background, his family in Ireland, when he started to play himself, about the death of the musical tradition back home; fieldworker notes that Frank Thornton takes a few digressions; how Thornton set up the Irish Musicians Association in America in l957 in conjunction with the parent body in Ireland; how Thornton organized a concert tour of Ireland by Irish and Irish American performers from Chicago, including discussion of the tour program (copy enclosed in fieldworker's final report); about the old days in Kerry where he was born; about Comhaltas Ceolteoiri Eireann (Musicians Association of Ireland) and its work; why Thornton came to America, his attitude to America, "a great country"; details of his immigration, where he came to and when (l929), where he worked, about getting citizenship papers, how he studied for and became a policeman, when he retired (l966); how Frank Thornton taught kids music, his own involvement in music over the years; about Francis O'Neill, the great Chicago music collector; about the musicians Thornton met when he came to Chicago, several are mentioned, all now dead; where those musicians would play; about clubs and associations; Thornton as co-founder of the Irish Musicians Association, its aims and philosophy, and now has 20 branches in the U.S. and Canada, and advertises on radio, there are 12 Irish radio programs in Chicago).; about the present-day musical situation among Irish Americans in Chicago; the sacrifices people make to pass on the traditional skills; Irish American musicians are seen as a great asset to the country, musical practice teaches good behavior to children; Thornton sees the biggest need among Chicago Irish Americans right now as financial assistance for schools of Irish traditional music, some kids cannot afford instruments, and there is a need for travelling concerts to be given across the country by top quality Irish performers to encourage and foster interest. Part 2 of 2-part interview with Frank Thornton about Irish Musicians Association and Irish music in Chicago, desire for documentary to encourage music, about state of singing and Gaelic language, state of Irish music in Chicago today is good and vital; topic sequence includes the past portrayal of Ireland in the media; Frank Thornton's ideas on how Ireland should be portrayed, the need for a good documentary film focusing on authentic Irish culture; Thornton thinks a movie of Irish American culture in Chicago should be made available; about the state of Irish singing in Chicago, the need for suitable places for musicians to perform; about the general lack of interest in this topic by mass media; Irish singing is now taught in Chicago, but not enough; there are two branches of Comhaltas in Chicago, seven in the Midwest, Frank Thornton is still active in Comhaltas activities; about Gaelic language classes, and a monthly mass in Gaelic; about Frank Thornton's performance in dance balls, on radio shows, in concerts, and his son Jim's collection; how Thornton feels the scene has been changed very much for the better, there are now 60 outstanding musicians in Chicago and a "couple of hundred coming up."
    - Interview with Peggy Roche Boyle about Irish dance, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 07, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20585A - AFS 20585B; RYA 0644; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of 2-part interview with Peggy Roche Boyle about Irish dance, including mention of her father Pat Roche who reprinted Francis O'Neill's book of Irish fiddle tunes in the 1930s, father's influence on his family, had the Harp and Shamrock Orchestra, about Peggy Roche Boyle's dancing and teaching, changes over time, methods, desire for a repertory theater; topic sequence includes her background, her family's Irish activities, about her father, Pat Roche, and his early involvement with dancing; about the World's Fair 1933, where Pat Roche helps organize the presentation of Irish culture; how Pat Roche kept the dancing alive, his involvement with the music scene and the reprinting of Francis O'Neill's collection of fiddle tunes in the 1930's; how Pat Roche transmitted his love of Ireland to his family, about other family members; about Pat Roche's Harp and Shamrock Orchestra, their recordings, his dances, other dancers who came to Chicago and from whom he learned; how Peggy Roche Boyle learned her first steps; about Pat Roche's school and his occupation; about Peggy Roche Boyle's participation in competitions, why she prefers teaching, when she started teaching, her negative attitudes toward competitions; about Peggy Roche Boyle's role in adult education in Irish dancing in St. Xavier's College; about the motivations of her students, where dancing is performed and why; about change over time in the nature of steps and techniques discussed, the reasons for change, teaching methods, steps not written down, labanotation problems, semi-formal method of transmission; about the role of Irish Dancing Teachers Commission; fieldworkers notes that at this point a child starts playing with the microphone around mother Peggy Roche Boyle's neck; about the standards and requirements of the Commission; problems with testing of teachers and teaching methods; about need for a Repertory Theatre for Irish dancing in Chicago.; about problems with dancers who never dance after they pass competition age, and the lack of suitable contexts; the number of people in Chicago learning Irish dancing; how a Repertory Theatre might be established, and potential problems, including personality problems, logistical problems, lack of finances; potential value of a study in Ireland with teachers and repertory theatres there; about the paucity of suitable rehearsal and performance contexts in Chicago. Part 2 of 2-part interview with with Peggy Roche Boyle about Irish dance, including Christmas dance exhibition, about dance style, girls attracted more than boys, some dissonance between musicians and dancers, influence of contests on style, conversation joined by husband Jimmy Boyle, about his repertory, influence of Clancy Brothers; topic sequence includes how Peggy Roche Boyle started her Christmas choreographed Irish dancing exhibition; about problems in researching authentic traditions, and the need for available folkloric source material; how she designed the show; why she only teaches certain material in her dancing classes; about Boyle's lack of knowledge of some of the old regional dances, there is a need for study in Ireland; about negative attitudes to set dances, resources may be available in Chicago, there are questions about the "right" and "wrong" ways to do things; how existing old style dancing resources in Chicago might be utilized; the need for finances seen as crucial in order to tap the talent out there, how informal dancing contexts might be stimulated; about Peggy Roche Boyle's dancing classes, 80 pupils, there is competition between dancing schools discussed; where pupils come from, what generation and gender; about the low number of males, the age at which pupils "drop off"; about the motivation of children and parents; how the school is publicized; about feelings on aspects of dancing style, the rift between musicians and dancers, a lack of mutual understanding has developed; about audience taste; Boyle has a negative response attitude to soft shoe dancing; why Irish American dancing standards are governed by attitudes among top dancers in Ireland; teachers are forced to enter their kids for competitions, they have "winning complexes"; the next segment is a conversation with Peggy Roche Boyle's husband, Jimmy Boyle, how he developed interest in his Irish background, how he started to dance, how he and Peggy met, his attitude to performing in pubs, when he learns, about his singing and his songs, where he gets them, the influence of the Clancy Brothers.
    - Interview with Mike Flannery about Irish American culture, Chicago, Illinois, May 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20586A; RYA 0645; 1 audiocassette, C-60
      Interview with Mike Flannery about Irish American culture, recorded out of doors (sound adversely affected by wind on microphone and jacket flapping); about influence of father, frustration at lack of interest in culture on the part of some Irish Americans; about Gaelic language, Irish Musicians Association, about context for individual's cultural understanding, relationship to politics, and other topics; this recording was made at the same time as the Fleadh Cheoil held at Bogan High School (call numbers AFC 1981/004: AFS 20587, AFS 20588, AFS 20589, AFS 20590, AFS 20591, and AFS 20592).
    - Recording of Fleadh Cheoil, held at Bogan High School, Chicago, Illinois, part 1, singing and instrumental competition; part 2, men's singing competition and fiddle and flute session; part 3, singing and instrumental competition; part 4, singing and instrumental competition; part 5, flute competition; part 6, flute competition and fiddle-accordion session, May 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20587 - AFS 20592; RXA 1022 - RXA 1027; 6 audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Part 1 of a 6-part recording made at the Fleadh Cheoil (singing and instrumental competition) held at Bogan High School; some recordings document the contest itself while others were made to the side; see the fieldworker's logs for more detail; recorded in a large hall: Noel Rice, flute, hornpipe; slow air, An Drimin Donn Dilis; then in a classroom, singing contest (microphone at a distance): sean nos (old style) singer, The Shores of Lough Bran; Mary Conway, My Blue Eyed Mountain Queen; Mary Conway, The Banks of the Lee; next: 14-16 age group singing competition: Liza Flatley, My Snowy Breasted Pearl and The Last Rose of Summer; Adjudication; next: Men's Senior Singing Competion: John Brennan, Long a Growing and Skibereen; James Skehan, The Banks of the Lee. Part 2 of a 6-part recording made at the Fleadh Cheoil (singing and instrumental competition) held at Bogan High School; some recordings document the contest itself while others were made to the side; see the fieldworker's logs for more detail; this recording includes Men's Senior Singing Competition in English: Kevin Henry, The Emigrant's Return and The Green Fieids of Dromore; Adjudication; next, context shifts to tiny alcove for a fiddle and flute session, sounds of traffic in background: Armin Barnett, fiddle, David Molk, flute, various reels and jigs. Part 3 of a 6-part recording made at the Fleadh Cheoil (singing and instrumental competition) held at Bogan High School; some recordings document the contest itself while others were made to the side; see the fieldworker's logs for more detail. Part 4 of a 6-part recording made at the Fleadh Cheoil (singing and instrumental competition) held at Bogan High School; some recordings document the contest itself while others were made to the side; see the fieldworker's logs for more detail; this recording includes a session with Liz Carroll, fiddle, Dan Collins, fiddle, and David Molk, flute, various reels; next, the Tin Whistle Competition (recorded at about 30-40 feet distance in school gym with audience a considerable distance from the chair on which the players sat and played for the adjudicators), some humming, banging, and shuffling noises; next, Seamus Coole, hornpipe, reel, jig (a nearby cassette momentarily turned on towards the end of the reel); next, Tom Masterson, tin whistle, slow air, jig, reel, hornpipe; next, unidentified player, tin whistle, hornpipe, slow air, jig, reel; Adjudication. Part 5 of a 6-part recording made at the Fleadh Cheoil (singing and instrumental competition) held at Bogan High School; some recordings document the contest itself while others were made to the side; see the fieldworker's logs for more detail; this recording includes the flute competition: Seamus Cooley (wooden flute), slow air, jig, hornpipe; reel; Kevin Henry (wooden flute), hornpipe, jig, slow air plus reel; Michael Flatley (wooden flute), jig, slow air, hornpipe, reel; Noel Rice (silver flute), slow air, hornpipe, jig, reel; David Molk (wooden flute), jigs, slow air. Part 6 of a 6-part recording made at the Fleadh Cheoil (singing and instrumental competition) held at Bogan High School, some recordings document the contest itself while others were made to the side; see the fieldworker's logs for more detail; from the flute competition: Noel Rice, adjudication; session with Liz Carroll, fiddle, Tommy McGuire, button accordion, spoons player with Liz Carroll; Liz Carroll and Tommy McGuire.
    - Interview with Pat Roche about Irish dance in Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 09, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20593A - AFS 20593B; RYA 0646; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of 2-part interview with Pat Roche about Irish dance in Chicago, Roche born in Ireland in 1905, came to America 1930, founded Harp and Shamrock Club; topic sequence includes where he was born, how he learned dancing at home, from whom he learned at home and in America; played football; when Roche came to Chicago (1930), he then joined a band and began teaching dancing, about some initial problems; about the system of teaching he developed; about his family back in Ireland, how many came to America, and why they emigrated; when he next went back to Ireland, when he was born (1905); about his involvement in organizing Irish American activities in Chicago over the years, music, dancing, boxing, Gaelic games, and his bands, including the Harp and Shamrock Club; about its activities; about dancing teachers in Chicago over the years, the benefits of Irish dancing to young people, it "develops their mind as well as their body"; about music and dance competitions over the years, initial problem in finding judges for competitions; about the Irish music that was played in public, e.g., in dance halls, and the types of instruments; story about how a young lad playing authentic Irish music fell under the influence of a wealthy patron and made good; about the Harp and Shamrock Orchestra, and its original (l933l members, by name, most are still alive, it is the only Ceili Band of that time; how the band made records, what company, what they were paid, how the band broke up, what happened to the members; Pat Roche incorporated the band and club name; about the World's Fair Irish Village; there has been no ceilidh bands since Harp and Shamrock until recently, convened for Feiseanna; how Pat Roche began his involvement with radio, which shows and stations over the years, he still has a show, he has been on radio steadily over the last 10 years, his show features culture, history, politics, and prominent Irish figures; how he recorded his dancing for commercial recordings. Part 2 of 2-part interview with Pat Roche about Irish dance in Chicago, Roche born in Ireland in 1905, came to America 1930, founded Harp and Shamrock Club, topics include development of Irish dancing style (tempo, steps, etc.) over the years; Pat Roche sees a constant progression; how he took his star pupils and taught them how to teach, "Most of the best teachers today are my pupils"; competitions are an important instrument for improvement in standards; why Pat Roche sees dancing as building character; discussion of his occupations since coming to America, in the Depression, he had his own business, peddled eggs, tea, coffee; then a fireman, then engineer, retired 1976; how Pat Roche found room for dancing, hard times, where he has lived in Chicago; how his children do and do not keep up Irish traditions; Pat Roche still dances, and thinks that the current state of dancing in Chicago is good, he sees dancing as keeping Irish Americans united; about step dancing and how Roche tried to get parents to learn set dancing, he feels Irish ceili dancing could be as popular in informal settings as square dancing; why dancing teachers don't teach the old sets, Pat Roche is dubious about the authenticity of the old country sets, adds comments on British exploitation of Ireland; more description of the Irish Village at the [1933 ?] World's Fair.
  - Subseries 5: Scandinavian
    - Interview with J. Harry and Josefa Andersøn regarding Norwegian American activities and customs, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 16, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20594A - AFS 20594B; RYA 0647; 2 audiocassette, C-90
      Part 1 of 2-part interview with Mr. and Mrs. Jan Harry and Josefa Andersen: 3416 N. Oak Park Ave., regarding immigration, Norwegian activities in Chicago, and survival of Norwegian customs; other topics include language, Christmas customs, Norwegian restaurant, "Den Norske Kafe," holidays including Sankthans or Midsommer; Syttenda Mai (Norwegian Independence Day), Fastelavn; Leif Ericsson Day and statue, seasonal food customs, "The Sunshine Singers," Norwegian language organizations, church in Chicago, Norwegians in trades and trade unions. Part 2; start of recording to 26 minutes elapsed time: part 2 of 2-part interview with Mr. and Mrs. Jan Harry and Josefa Andersen: 3416 N. Oak Park Ave., regarding Norwegian American customs, Wheaton College, religious organizations and the Salvation Army, veterans association, and immigrant songs.
    - Interview with Paul Sveinbjörn about Icelandic American activities and customs, Evanston, Illinois, part 1-2, May 16, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20594B - AFS 20595A; RYA 0647-0648; 2 audiocassette, C-90
      From 26 minutes elapsed time to end of recording: part 1 of a 2-part interview with Mr. and Mrs. Paul Svejnbjorn Johnson, 936 Sheridan Rd., Evanston, 60206, about Icelandic activities in Chicago, and survival of Icelandic customs. Svejnbjorn Johnson is the consul of Iceland and Mrs. Johnson is a cultural leader in the Icelandic American community. Topic include occupations of Icelanders in Chicago, language, food customs, National Day, Icelandic participation in Scandinavian churches, Leif Ericsson Day, Christmas customs, regular visits to Iceland, a traditional fish dish and "the Cod War." Part 2 of a 2-part interview with Mr. and Mrs. Paul Svejnbjorn Johnson, 936 Sheridan Rd., Evanston, 60206, about Icelandic activities in Chicago, and survival of Icelandic customs.
    - Interview with Olga Lejondahl and Ruth Peterson regarding Swedish painting in Chicago area, Evanston, Illinois, part 1-2, May 17, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20596A - AFS 20596B; RYA 0649; 2 audiocassette, C-90
      Part 1 of a 2-part interview with Mrs. Olga Lejondahl and Mrs. Ruth Peterson, Evergreen Park; topics include Swedish painting in Chicago area; Mrs. Lejondahl is a Dalarmalar (may be Dala paintings or kurbits paintings from Dalarna province), as well as a mural, portrait, and landscape painter; Mrs. Peterson is her landlady; discussion of Lejondahl's background, immigration, origin, beginning of painting, styles, brushes and paint, murals on order, about immigration to Chicago and early work there, visits to Sweden, family there and in U.S., other Swedish traditions, incl. food, Christmas, etc. Part 2 of a 2-part interview with Mrs. Olga Lejondahl and Mrs. Ruth Peterson, Evergreen Park; closing fragment of interview, duration 4 minutes.
    - Interview with Ray Nilsen regarding musical background and repertoire, also Norwegian musical and dance activities in Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 17, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20597A - AFS 20597B; RYA 0650; 2 audiocassette, C-90
      Part 1 of a 2-part audiocassette recording of and interview with and performances by Ray Nilsen, 6059 N. Newburg, Chicago, IL. 60631; additional segments of this event were recorded on open-reel tapes at call numbers AFC 1981/004: AFS 20598 and AFS 20599; topics in this part include musical background and repertoire, also Norwegian musical and dance activities in Chicago; Mr. Nilsen is an accordionist, singer, and choir director; discussion of learning the music, playing in the old country, music lessons in Chicago, father's musical background, occupations in U.S. attitudes towards other Norwegian music, source of accordion repertoire, fiddling and dancing in Norway, differences in Chicago and Norway repertoire, revival of older music, Norwegian dance-groups in Chicago, "The Sunshine Singers," Salvation Army Scandinavian Night, Norwegian choirs and choral societies, church and dance music, Norwegian American holidays, Christmas parties for kids, Sjomannsvalsar (sailors waltzes), emigrants songs, Syttenda Mai (Norwegian Independence Day) and Norwegian patriotic songs; introduction to the musical portion of this recording and performances that include Se Nu Dansar Bestefar (Grandfather's Waltz), Kostarvalsen, Nidaran, Lejkaringen, Heimhugg' Schottische, Poul Sine Hans (with vocals), Springdans, Seksnummer Reel, Klapdans, Handfei ("Soldier's Joy" variant), Ekereel, Fussel, and En Sjomann Elskar Havets Brus. Part 2 of a 2-part audiocassette recording of and interview with and performances by Ray Nilsen, 6059 N. Newburg, Chicago, IL. 60631; additional segments of this event were recorded on open-reel tapes at call numbers AFC 1981/004: AFS 20598 and AFS 20599; performances in this part include Den Klare Aftanstjerne, Lapplander song (no title given), Piende Visa, Christmas song (title not given), Jeg ar sa Glad av Julan Kam, Dejlige ar Jordan; conversation about psalmodikon (or psalmodicon, musical instrument).
    - Performances by Ray Nilsen, accordion and vocals, part 1, with Leandra Nilsen, piano, Chicago, Illinois; and part 2, May 17, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20598 - AFS 20599; RXA 1028 - 1029; 2 audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Part 1 of a 2-part open-reel tape recording of and interview with and performances by Ray Nilsen, accordion and vocals, and Leandra Nilsen, piano, 6059 N. Newburg, Chicago, IL. 60631; additional segments of this event were recorded on an audiocassette at call numbers AFC 1981/004: AFS 20597a and AFS 20597b; selections in this part include song; waltz; and the hymn "Beautiful Savior" sung in English and Norwegian, piano and vocals; duration of this recording 4:30 minutes. Part 2 of a 2-part open-reel tape recording of and interview with and performances by Ray Nilsen, accordion and vocals, and Leandra Nilsen, piano, 6059 N. Newburg, Chicago, IL. 60631; additional segments of this event were recorded on an audiocassette at call numbers AFC 1981/004: AFS 20597a and AFS 20597b; selections in this part include "Se Nu Danser Bestefar" (Grandfather's Waltz), followed by comments on instruments; "Kostervalsen"; "Nideron"; "Lejkaringen, Heimbugg" (schottische); "Poul Sine Hons" followed by comments; "Springdans"; "Seksnummer Reel" (polka); "Klapdans"; "Handfei" (variant of' Soldier's Joy); "Ekereel"; "Fussol" (dance for couples, variant of' Turkey in the Straw); "En Sjomann Elskar Havets Brus" [En sjöman älskar havets våg, ja vågornas brus] (waltz, sailor's farewell to his girl); waltz (sailor's song, with comments); "Den Klare Aftanstjerne" (waltz); Lapplander song; "Piende Visa" followed by story.
    - Interview with Kurt Mathiasson at the Swedish-American Museum about Swedish traditions and music in Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, May 18, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20600A - AFS 20600B; RYA 0651; 2 audiocassette, C-90